<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands condition considered, and bewailed. Wherein, the obstructions of peace, and the wayes essayed to effect it are rightly stated, and argued, between the Parliament, and the Scots Commissioners. With many observations on their late papers, concerning the foure bils, and propositions sent to the King. Imprimatur, Gilb. Mabbot.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A83952</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E2954</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E423_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201918</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862400</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862400</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161405</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A83952)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161405)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 67:E423[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands condition considered, and bewailed. Wherein, the obstructions of peace, and the wayes essayed to effect it are rightly stated, and argued, between the Parliament, and the Scots Commissioners. With many observations on their late papers, concerning the foure bils, and propositions sent to the King. Imprimatur, Gilb. Mabbot.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert White,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Jan 18. 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: the 8 in imprint date crossed out and date altered to 1647.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Peace --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Foreign relations --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England --  Foreign relations --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161405:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ENGLANDS CONDITION CONSIDERED, AND BEWAILED.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WHEREIN,</hi> The obſtructions of Peace, and the wayes eſſayed to effect it are rightly ſtated, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued, between the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and the <hi>Scots COMMISSIONERS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WITH Many obſervations on their late Papers, concerning the foure Bils, and PROPOSITIONS ſent to the <hi>KING.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>In bellis civilibus etiam poſt partam victoriam, non ſtatim pax, ſed varius metus, &amp; diſcordia.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>Tacitus <hi>lib. ſecun. Hiſt.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Imprimatur, <hi>Gilb. Mabbot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert White, Jan</hi> 18. 1648</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:161405:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:161405:2"/>
            <head>ENGLANDS CONDITION, CONSIDERED, AND BEWAILED.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is no time to make Apologies, and Prefaces, to have Epiſtles dedicatorie, and unto the Reader, to write under the <hi>Roſe,</hi> or to ſhadow diſcourſes with darke and knotty reſemblances; wee have been premiſing, and prefacing all this while; plain <hi>Engliſh</hi> is beſt, for we are like elſe to loſe our own Dialect ſhortly. The name of Liberty of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and Priviledges of <hi>Parliaments</hi> will ſoone be worne out, as the old Saxon language, and refined into Prerogative and Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. And our lawes which were firſt written in <hi>French,</hi> are like for better underſtanding them, to be reprinted in the ſame, with the <hi>Scots</hi> marginall notes.</p>
            <p>I am ſoone fallen into a lamentable diſcourſe before I am aware, and my trembling pen would faine haſten over it; But I muſt be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious. Diſtractions and confuſions in States, and Kingdoms, are not trifles. He that will view the condition of poore <hi>England,</hi> had need have a heart made of wax, and eyes of water, and bovvels of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion. If men knew vvhere they are come to, they would ſoone know how to thinke themſelvs miſerable; wee have gone a ſeven years march in a State diſguiſe, and after a long round are fairly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced into our old condition, and it were well (ſay ſome) if vve are no worſe; the ſcene is changed but the play the ſame. That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and gallant ſpirit, which heretofore wrought in true <hi>Engliſh</hi> hearts, for liberty, and Priviledges, is now down, and the old un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manklike
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:161405:3"/> puſillanimitie come upon us, with an addition of ſtupidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and inſenſiblenes; we have loſt our bloud, and now we are like to loſe our hearts; we have been almoſt deſtroyed by a civill warre, and may be undone by unſound peace; But I muſt be cautious, I ſhall be accounted a foole for my labour, yet I muſt be honeſt, I ſhall only ſpeak what wiſe men think, and honeſt men feele; if more were done, leſſe would be ſpoken Our greateſt worke hath been to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe our ſelves; we have acted <hi>magno conatu, magnas nugas,</hi> ſowne the winde, and brought forth the whirlewind. Certainly we have loſt that reflect act of our underſtanding, by which, they ſay, the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall ſoule is made happy. Recollect your ſelves what you have been doing ſo long a time, where you are going, vvhat new deſigns are on you. We have eſcaped the Spaniſh Inquiſition, we hope, But hovv nigh you are to <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> you little thinke. What is become of that golden fleece (<hi>Liberty</hi>) vvhich you ſo gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantly fought for? where are the trophies of your conqueſt? vvho will pitie us? We have ſeen our maladie, but know not our reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; we know how to be miſerable, and have found out an eaſie way to it, but yet cannot ſee our way to be happy. Our enemies are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, and now vve are falling out vvith our friends; Its harder to reconcile our ovvn party, then to deſtroy the Kings. Our wounds are opened, none wholly cured; our nakedneſſe diſcovered, and nothing to cover it. What ſhall become of poore <hi>England?</hi> wee have wonne liberty, but dare not weare it; the victory is got, but we cannot agree about the ſpoyle? Formerly we knew our enemies, now vve neither know them nor our friends. Seven years experience of tumults and war is ſufficient (one would think) to learne us the way to a happie peace, vve have not wanted time, or wayes to know our enemies and our friends. Providence hath helpt us through a bloudy warre, and now diviſion would help us to a diſhoneſt peace, But theſe are too melancholy meditations; if men had been as honeſt as they pretended to be wiſe, vve ſhould have no ſuch ſad things to work upon. But let us warily conſider how vve are come into this condition, on whom lies the fault. Aske our gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees who ſtear at the Helme. Some blame one, ſome another, I blame none, and yet all; I have nothing to ſay to particulars, vve have too much in generals,</p>
            <p>Some lay the fault on his Majeſty, And the truth is he hath enough
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:161405:3"/> to be charged withall, yet ſince the conqueſt, he hath been under re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, and could not ſo poſſitively hinder, except you grant him his negative voyce, yet he cannot be altogether excuſed, he hath done what in him lies in ſuch a condition, &amp; his private influences and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiations have not been ordinary, but we have too much to charge him with on the old account.</p>
            <p>Others lay the blame on the Parliament (and here we ſhall not want Votes) they ſay they have ſought themſelves, not the Kingdom: but wee may give our enemies too great advantage of us by ſuch jealouſies. Its true, they are the rock to which we have lookt for our ſalvation, they have promiſed us our liberty, they can procure it, and it were to be wiſhed they could waſh their hands cleane of all things; yet all muſt not be laid on the Parliament, but a faction in it: they are a great body, made up of divers and unſutable ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and labour with abundance of infirmities, and paſſe through thoſe difficulties vulgar eyes ſee not, yet to be plain, more might have been done then is; had ſome of them been leſſe imployed, and intereſſed in affaires, more would have been acted for us: thoſe ſad retreats they have made of late, is too ominous, of great diſtempers even among them: but I ſhall rather pray for them, then ſpeak any more of their frailties. Others wipe away all blame from both, and lay all on the Army; poor men, they have born the heat of the War, and now muſt needs have the blame of the Peace: its our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery that we have none to diſtruſt, but theſe which have been moſt faithfull; but yet it may be they are not wholly free, though I think in an equall diſtribution little will come to their ſhare; they have been good ſervants, what they may prove when they become ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, I know not; ſome mens conditions alter their ſpirits, but we have little cauſe to ſuſpect them; where ever the blame lies, the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery is like to lye on us: the truth is, It hath been the deſigne of ſome to bring us where we are; and the ill foreſight of others; we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not go ſo far back, as to queſtion the truth of our cauſe, (God hath cleared that from heaven,) but ſome men may queſtion their princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. God hath acted for us in the VVar, and now men act in the Peace: we have not come into this condition <hi>per ſaltum,</hi> as many Dunces are made Doctors; but have gradually &amp; inſenſibly been led into it by the cunning artifice of ſome maſter builders in the black Art: As many an ignorant diſputer granting this, and that, is by an
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:161405:4"/> ingenious Sophiſter, brought before he is aware, into a confuting abſurdity.</p>
            <p>Let us caſt our eyes back, but ſince the end of this War with the Royall partie, and we ſhall finde ſome ſteps, wherein the ſecret con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivers of our ruine have walkt. When the King ſaw he could hold out no longer in Arms, he betakes himſelf to his ſhifts, leaves <hi>Oxford</hi> to a confiding party, and betakes himſelf to the Scots Army as his ſanctuary, (a plot agreed on to mutuall advantage) the King gives in Newark at the deſire of the <hi>Scots,</hi> is carried to Newcaſtle, and by this time <hi>Oxford</hi> is likewiſe ſurrendred, and the War ended, but things end not ſo: we want an enemy in the field, one muſt be made at home. Factions are raiſed, diſcontents fomented againſt the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, under the name of Independents, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Some principles infuſed into the City of deſigns againſt them, they are ſet on to go to the Parliament w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Petitions, Remonſtrances for the ſetling Presbyterian Government, the Miniſters made to ſtir up the people againſt ſuch &amp; ſuch men, under ſuch names as they know would incenſe ſufficiently; ſome of our <hi>Engliſh,</hi> great men (who knew not how to be high enough) joyn Counſels with the <hi>Scots,</hi> under pretence of maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Covenant, and ſetting up Presbyteriall Government, and that the City might be made ſure, the <hi>Scots</hi> are ſent to Court them, with Letters from the Eccleſiaſticks and Civils, to congratulate their faithfulneſſe to this Cauſe, to ſtir them up to the diligent proſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Covenant; things grow to ſome height, (as ſuch fire will not want fewell,) and are ripe for action, they get Ordinances for preſſing all men to take the Covenant anew, that none ſhall be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in any office in Church or State, but he which will take the Covenant, (and that over again) and ſubmit to the Presbyteriall Government, and all this with an eye to the Army, whom they knew how to inſnare; and as things were thus laid, ſo they were not negligent in the execution, the City of <hi>London</hi> muſt firſt begin as a patern to the reſt, caſt out their old Militia, get power to chooſe a new fit for the deſign, and becauſe the Common Counſel is to order the Civill Affaires, as the other the Military, that muſt be Moddled into the ſame image; all that were thought but to be of the other partie, or favorers of them, caſt out: All this while the King is at <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> indeavoring to ingage the <hi>Scots</hi> Army for him, and how far he prevailed I could tell you, but that we had ſuch
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:161405:4"/> a peaceable parting at laſt. While the King was ingaging for him the party in <hi>England</hi> had another eye on that Army, as the Army of the Covenant, and to have kept them to Ballance this Army which lay in their way; but things were not yet ripe, they were too great a power to be conquered by force, eſpecially having been juſt then raiſed with the glory of ſo great a Conqueſt, and the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes crying out of their burthens under all the ſeverall Armies, which were inſupportable; counſels are joyned, and agreed to the march of the Scots Army, and delivery up of the King, on the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle conſideration of 400000 l. The King ſhall ſtill be kept as a reſerve to make advantage of at laſt; But now the <hi>Scots</hi> are gone, and that feare over, what they could nor doe by force, they will do by guile, the Army is ſtill the eye-ſore, that darkned the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Splendor of ſome great ones who had formerly been in Command, and had done Service, but had not the happineſſe of being totall Conquerors; nothing leſſe is indeavoured then to breake this Army; many ways they eſſayed, but the maine was under pretence of relieving <hi>Ireland,</hi> (a deſigne, not only faire, but ſo honeſt in it ſelfe, that all men cryed it up,) but how is this to be carryed on? who but <hi>Waller</hi> and <hi>Maſſey,</hi> (men who had an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veterate hatred againſt this Army, they thinking themſelves too much clouded by them) are ſent downe to treat with the Army about it, and propoſe queſtions and conditions to the Souldiers to be under their Command: the one as Generall, the other as Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant generall: The reflexion of this carriage in the thoughts of the Souldiery, cannot but make them look about them, that ſome deſigne was on foot againſt them, by their and the Kingdoms ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; eſpecially ſeeing the Parliament ſhould wave them, who had but even now done them ſuch faithfull ſervice, and not ſo much as thinke them fit to be further imployed in any Service, eſpecially to command their owne Souldiers; they reſent the buſineſſe, obſerve the Deſigne, and are ſtrangely united, to give a Negative Anſwer, that none of them would ſtirre without their owne Commanders; But with either the Generall, or Lieutenant Gen <hi>Crumwel,</hi> would all march at the Parliaments pleaſure; yet ſeeing this will not doe, ſome other way muſt be taken: Mony for Arreares is offered to thoſe which will leave the Army, (on which ſome fell off, but no conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable number,) as they ſought to divide, they unite; yet when
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:161405:5"/> this would not doe, but they ſaw they were not ſo meal mouthd as the reſt, they muſt be disbanded as unneceſſary, and a burthen to the Kingdome, and that without their Arreares, and in parts, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thoſe requiſites which belonged to their honour and ſecurity; thus would they have the firſt fruits of this Conqueſt, begin in the diſhonourable disbanding of the Conquerours. But the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers grew acquainted with theſe deſignes, and get heart, reſolve to ſtand on their guard, and to knit them the more, chooſe Agitators out of every Regiment, for the better ordering and communicating of things to each other, draw up Petitions to the Parliament, which by the ſtrenuous negotiation and power of thoſe firſt deſigners a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, was cenſured as Treaſonable, and the Authors as Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; which could not but incenſe, when they ſaw favours and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices ſo ſoon forgotten: yet all this which was laid for diviſion is the advantage for their union, and they randevouz with much unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and courage, and were at laſt owned by the Generall, and the reſt of the Commanders, who for a while were ſhy becauſe of the newneſſe and hazard of the buſineſſe. Things being thus in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and in that poſture, they bethink what may be of concernment to them before they are disbanded, expecting to have no more after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, then they could make ſure at firſt; they therefore propoſe to the Parliament what belonged to them as Souldiers: And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this advantage, ſeeing they fought for the good of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, make an Eſſay by Propoſitions to the Parliament for the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Kingdome alſo; drew up charges againſt eleven of thoſe Members who were the chief Actors in the deſign; upon which, they, at their owne deſires, had leave given by the Parliament, to withdraw; but things thus acting, new Counſels are ſet on foot. Firſt, the King muſt be lookt unto, and got away either into <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> or <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſo it was endeavoured, in the mean while (unknown unto the Army, as the Generall profeſt in his Letter to the Speaker) by the particular Act of Cornet <hi>Ioyce,</hi> (one of no great head for to lay any deep deſigne) who was ſent out with a party of horſe towards <hi>Oxford,</hi> but would needs go viſit his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, the King was voluntarily brought to the Army, which though it was ſtrange to them, and they were ſtartled at it, yet they thought they might make an advantage of him as well as others, at leaſt to keep him from being in a Faction againſt them.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:161405:5"/> But that deſigne is not yet broken, all this while Reformadoes, Apprentiſes, and others are ſecretly liſted, great ſums of money paid to the old Officers of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and <hi>Wallers,</hi> and <hi>Maſſeyes</hi> Army, and things grew ſo high, as a great company of them beſet the Houſe of Commons kept them in till nine of the clock at night, with threatning words make them recall their Ordinances, vote in the King which made the Speakers of both Houſes, with many of the honeſt Members fly to the Army for ſafety: Theſe men are ſtill in the City ſtirring up the <hi>Militia,</hi> and Common counſell, framing a new Army, and thoſe ſeeds which were formerly ſown by the <hi>Scots</hi> and them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> come up into blades<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Pikes, they ſtand in a Poſture of War to defend themſelves and oppoſe the Army, which never intended to come nigh them, unleſſe provoked; the Army hearing of theſe doings march towards the City, and when they came to <hi>Windſor</hi> accidentally met with the Speakers, and the reſt of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the fled Members; after congratulation and mutuall expreſſes of love, and joy to ſee one another, the Army Rendevouz at <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlow heath,</hi> and reſolve to march to the City, who prevented them with termes ſutable to peace, (out of what principle we will not diſpute) the Members were brought to the Houſe in peace the Army marches through the City in peace, and now things ſeemed to be hopefull; but though the eleven Members were gone, yet the Spirit was not gone with them; though the City durſt not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Army, they will ſtarve them, and make them odious, and a burthen to the Kingdome, therefore they will lend no money, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay their contributions, not pay their Arreares that the Army is looked on as our miſery, the Countries undone and all buſineſſe retarded above, by the remainder of that party, that while we look for peace, behold threatnings of another War, and we are now brought to ſuch a paſſe, that he is a wiſe man that knowes what to propoſe firſt. The King is gone from us to the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Wight,</hi> and there he takes time to weigh his deſignes upon us; Propoſitions are gone to him, di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ed by ſome, and proteſted againſt by the <hi>Scots;</hi> coldly, and cunningly anſwered by himſelfe: Thus have we hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomly made way for our own miſery, we know not our own ſtrength, and therefore muſt divide, and with <hi>David</hi> number the people. Some men have plaid their own games, and now leave us to pay ſtakes; diviſions are growne ſo high among our ſelves,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:161405:6"/> that our common enemy growes high in their hopes, and expect a turn, wherein they may be a third party, and have one caſt more for to recover their compoſitions. When ſhall we learn to be wiſe? But I crave pardon I have made this digreſſion, but its to ſhew you the way you are come to this miſery, which if God prevent not, will make us the ſpectacle of the Nations.</p>
            <p>But what is become all this while of our Brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> that they have been out of the tranſaction? You will have enough of them anon. The truth is, they have not been idle all this while in the City. And not unknowne, how they have endeavoured to bring <hi>Edinbrough</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> and <hi>Hallyrudehouſe</hi> to <hi>White-hall;</hi> they love us ſo well, that they vvould not only be one with us in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, but Priviledge, and would gladly have the name of great <hi>Britain</hi> comprehend us all. And becauſe our diviſions were not wide enough, out of their ſuperabundant love to us, they caſt in bones betvveen us, and publickly reflect on our ſtrength (the high Court of <hi>Parliament,</hi> and the Army) to ſtrengthen the great ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities that is in the moſt againſt them, that we may have a ſecond need of them to be Umpires. But now before I am aware I am faln into the boſome of the <hi>Scots</hi> Declaration, a Declaration of the <hi>Scots</hi> indeed, and of other men too; by vvhich I hope all true hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Engliſh men</hi> will take a copy of their countenance towards us. Yet I ſhall not meddle much with the contents of it; the <hi>Parliament</hi> no doubt will ſo fully doe Juſtice in it. Only in the generall I ſhall take leave to animadvert ſomething. We may better ſpeak plaine <hi>Engliſh</hi> then they. I take notice of a grand De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne driven on againſt the <hi>Parliament</hi> and Army, by thoſe who wait for our ruine; and of which this Declaration is but a Manifeſto to the world. <hi>Viz.</hi> to make the <hi>Parliament</hi> low in the eyes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and render them diſtaſtefull, that ſo the King may have the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer way to his old power; ſo likevviſe to render the Army, ſo intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable a burthen as that the Kingdome cannot ſubſiſt under them; and to carry on this the more ſecretly, the Covenant, and Religion are made the veiles.</p>
            <p>Two things I cannot but take notice of as generall in that Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. Firſt, their ſo often zealous (if not ſuperſtitious) mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Covenant, more then tvventy times in one leafe, as if all Religion were vv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> up in that, that it were not only the compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:161405:6"/> but the exact forme of all divinity. And as if they would make the world beleive, that they preferre the Covenant before all their own Intereſts, and Deſignes, whereas I feare, they, and too many more, have made it but a State trick to deceive poore igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant devout ſoules. Its a great queſtion whether they think ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the Covenant of Grace. I confeſſe vve have no reaſon to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of taking the Covenant, we tooke it honeſtly, and ſincerely, little thinking the uſe which vvould be made of it, to inſnare us to the <hi>Scots</hi> deſignes. I would only deſire our Brethren to recollect themſelves, how they kept Covenant vvith our Commiſſioners in the North, and then they will have little heart to charge it on us in the South. I could name the particulars, but that I am loth to diſturb the honourable Commiſſioners in their Religion.</p>
            <p>Secondly I cannot but take notice, (as all men elſe ſhould) of the tenderneſſe of our Brethren, and the deep refenting of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of <hi>England,</hi> and that in ſo neer and intimate a way, that they neglect their owne; chiefly inſiſting, purely and nakedly on theſe things which concerne our Kingdome, and fcarce mentioning their own. This is brotherly love indeed; But leſt we ſhould be ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, they fairely ſalve a miſtake with this, that they would have the <hi>Militia</hi> in the hands of the King, and the <hi>Parliament</hi> and Kingdom lye again at his Majeſties feet for a generall pardon; for ſo they ſhall ſoone if once he get that power. And now ſince I am falne on this, it will not be much out of the way, to ſpend a word or two, in diſtinguiſhing how farre <hi>Scotland</hi> is to meddle in the concernments of <hi>England</hi> by the Treaty. Let this be laid as a foundation, that let the union be never ſo nigh; it doth not neceſſarily imply a commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication of properties, there are intire and proper incommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Priviledges which are reſerved to both: As between man and wife, which is the nigheſt conjunction, there are titles and honours which are proper to each perſon, which both have the benefit of, but not the particular propriety in. The union between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> can be only in thoſe things which are of common concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to both, which belongs to the very being, and well being of the union; they are notwithſtanding two Kingdomes, and have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Lawes, and Priviledges peculiar to each, and which neither may meddle in. Novv let it be ſeriouſly vveighed, that to preſſe our uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on too farre, even to an introaching on the properties of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:161405:7"/> is to make our union uncomfortable, and to lay a foundation for a breach; Now vvhat concernes us in particular, and doth not touch on the Intereſts of the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> muſt be left to the <hi>Parliament</hi> to determine, as vvhat concerns them to their <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi> That which concerns us are eſpecially our Lawes, the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> the <hi>Militia;</hi> and theſe are ſo ours, as that you may turne <hi>Scotland</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> and make an Identity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us, before they can meddle with them; and doubtleſſe the <hi>Parliament</hi> cannot chooſe but reſent it highly, that any Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners either of <hi>Scotch,</hi> or of any Kingdome in the world, ſhall take upon them to declare and proteſt againſt the ſending thoſe things in Propoſitions, vvhich is their birth right, and undoubted Priviledge, and which they can have no competitors in, without the higheſt breach of their truſt. And the Commiſſioners might as well have proteſted againſt any Ordinance made by the <hi>Parliament</hi> for Exciſe, or againſt their making a new great Seale, as againſt any of theſe foure Propoſitions, vvhich are ſolely the concernments of <hi>England,</hi> and have not ſo much, as the leaſt aſpect on the Intereſt of <hi>Scotland,</hi> nor influence upon the Treaty between the Kingdomes. And as to that clauſe in the Treaty vvhich ſaith, that we ſhall not make either peace or warre without each others adviſe and conſent; It muſt be ſtill meant in theſe things wherein our mutuall Intereſts are contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: for elſe we have covenanted our ſelves into a faire condition, that the <hi>Scots</hi> negative voyce, though in thoſe things which eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally concerne our own Kingdome, may hinder our happineſſe as they pleaſe; ſo that we muſt be beholding unto them for their conſent in that vvhich God, and nature hath inveſted us withall; How much ſhould vve have been overſeen to deny his Majeſty a negative voyce (knowing the hazard of it) and give it to the <hi>Scots?</hi> You ſee how our exigencies have brought us into inconveniences; vve have, of our indulgence, and brotherly reſpect made them privie to all our Counſels, and Priviledges, and they now claime an Intereſt in them; I doubt that if this <hi>Parliament</hi> be diſſolved, our Brethren will chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge the right of calling the next, that vve ſhall neither have Law, nor Priviledge without their conſent. The laſt year they claimed a Right to the diſpoſing of the Kings perſon in <hi>England;</hi> and novv they claime a Right to diſpoſe of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions, though purely in matters of our own Kingdome. They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:161405:7"/> fair, if the progreſſe be ſutable, vve ſhall have neither Law, nor Liberty, but what the <hi>Scots</hi> Commſſioners ſhall vote for us; But that by the by, though they make it the great ſcope of their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration. We have now ſeen our miſery, how vve lye at the brink of great dangers, ſome would divide us into more parties, then all the wiſe men among us know how to make up; and what advantage men are taking daily to make the Breaches wider, while others lie at the catch to diſadvantage us.</p>
            <p>Let us now ſee vvhat may doe us good, (if we be not paſt cure) we have been long time in warre, its time for us novv to think of a peace; and I know that is in the expectation of all men. Peace is a ſweet word, eſpecially after war, yet we had it a long time, and could not prize it, we have been long unacquainted with it, and now have loſt the way to it; we all agree on the thing, if we could on the termes; Indeed to ſome the name of peace is as an unpleaſant ſound, there be fiſh that cannot live but in troubled waters; others love peace, but have too common apprehenſions of it. I love peace, and I hate it, I love it as I find it wrapt up in the armes of truth, I hate it as its in iniquity, and on baſe termes; let others take it, I ſhall not envie them. I would men loved truth as I love peace. I love that peace which may requite the bloud which hath been ſhed to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe it, ſuch a peace as may keep God, and the Goſpel with us; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other will be but a foundation of a future warre; Its better ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a little to ſettle a good peace; Its better ſuffer a little longer, then get a peace that will end in greater warre; We know what vvill be the worſt to ſtand to ſuch conditions as may produce a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid peace, but we knovv not vvhat will be the end of an unſound peace.</p>
            <p>Divers, as they have deſired, ſo have aſſaied to bring forth peace; the wayes and means, with the ends they act, are not ſo conſonant, wee will a little conſider what is propoſed in ſuch a tranſaction. The Parliament and the <hi>Scots</hi> are the great Agitators of this work, but with different principles and ends, as we ſhall ſee anon: the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ſtick to the way of Propoſitions, only thoſe for ſecurity tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into bils: the <hi>Scots</hi> urge a perſonall treaty, and therefore have followed it hard, that no other way may be thought on, yea, have proteſted againſt the Parliaments way of Addreſſe, though they ſo far condeſcend, as to bring down the number of Bils to four, and to treat the reſt.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:161405:8"/>
            <p>Let us conſider ſoberly, which way is moſt likely to effect the end. In generall, I much queſtion, whether the <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>Hearts</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Clubs</hi> will make a good match, eſpecially when the <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>Diamonds</hi> is competi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reſſe. But eſpecially this muſt be taken in, what the nature of that peace is, we are to indeavor. That peace which muſt make us happy, muſt be a ſafe, honourable, and well grounded Peace. The Queſtion is, whether in a perſonall treaty ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Scots</hi> indeavor, ſuch a peace may be eſtabliſhed? they urge much for it, and quote former Declarations of the Parliament; but what may be for the good of <hi>Scotland</hi> properly, and as in its own conſtitution is one thing, and what for <hi>England</hi> is another; I doubt whether a peace grounded only on ſuch things as are contained in the generall Treaty, will ſerve for all the particulars we need have granted for our own Kingdome; ſuch a peace muſt be procured, as will confirm our union with them, and incourage our friends, diſcountenance our enemies; that may unite us at home, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> others abroad.</p>
            <p>Now what way is moſt ſutable to ſuch an end, is the queſtion: Let us take firſt into conſideration, the perſonall treaty, which our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren are ſuch ſticklers for, how like it is to produce ſuch a peace.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Conſider the probable good that will come out of ſuch a treaty in reference to this end. The Parliament have ſent Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which they have thought fit for the future good, and ſecurity of the Kingdome, without the granting which, we can neither be happy, nor hopefull; they have altered ſome of them; and qualified them, more to the ſenſe of the King, rather then Kingdom, that it might take better with him, a long time he hath had to conſider of them, ſome he is willing to grant, which are leſſe materiall, others he refuſeth his conſent to; as being againſt his honour, (we are ſure for our good) the Parliament cannot but ſtill inſiſt on the ſubſtance of the Propoſitions, they muſt be the matter of the treaty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Now if his Majeſty after ſo long time of conſideration; cannot conſent to our demands, how can we believe he will when he ſhall treat in perſon, when the ſame things are urged and ſtuck unto? for either the Parliament muſt treat only on what the King ſhall propound, or elſe frame new Propoſitions of a different ſenſe; not ſo good for the Kingdome, or elſe a perſonall treaty will be no more then a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mallity, or complement; which yet may be hazzardous to us; to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:161405:8"/> ſpeake truth, the King can write plainer then ſpeake; and if we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have his hand and ſeale, how can we expect his heart.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Neither is it honourable for the Parliament after ſo long waiting for his Majeſties conſent, now to admit his perſon with freedom and honour to a perſonall treaty, wherein they muſt be fain to retract all their former Propoſitions, or have the ſame negative anſwer to the moſt materiall concernments of their privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and our liberty; they have made too many ſad retreats alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, to their own diſhonour and the Kingdoms diſadvantage. Its our unhappineſſe that his Majeſty hath put himſelf in ſuch a capacity, as he is yet to be looked on under the notion of enmity; and whereas the <hi>Scots</hi> urge the Parliaments own Declarations, they muſt conſider times and ſeaſons: can the Parliament in honour treat on equall tearms now, as when the King had an Army to ballance their power? It was the utmoſt the King deſired, to come to a perſonall treaty, when he had his greateſt ſtrength, and doubtleſſe he knew his own ends then as now. But it will be objected, can any way be more honourable then to treat perſonally with the King? I anſwer, that is moſt Honourable to the Parliament, which holds them to their firſt principles of juſtice and liberty, and keeps up their reſolutions for the good of the Kingdome, and the perſonall treaty will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute much to this, however if it be honourable touching Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, we muſt have it firme, in regard of ſecurity, which is the Third thing to be conſidered ſeriouſly, How ſafe it may be; though the Commiſſioners ſeem to make it out of Queſtion, they muſt give us leave to feare it, eſpecially when ſo many heart-burnings are already among us, and fire balls ready for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> up and down City and Countrey. It is a ſad condition we are brought in, that what his Majeſty thinkes honourable for his perſon, is not ſafe for us. How can we thinke to gaine any thing by a perſonall trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or have ſecurity of any good by it, ſeeing he refuſeth to take the Covenant? and here I wonder our Brethren, can diſpence with their Cauſe, to truſt the Kings perſon in ſuch a Treaty, when he refuſeth and proteſteth againſt the Covenant; they highly charge the Parliament for that they left it out in the Propoſitions, and yet our Brethren can willingly let it out of the perſonall Treaty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The truth is, they would gladly have his perſon with us, for they know they can never have him further off them, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:161405:9"/> what they can of the Parliament, how they would try what they can get from the King. But how ſafe it may be for us in theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetled times, vvhen moſt are diſcontented, and ſeeme to be taken vvith any thing vvhich is nevv, and ſeems but to ſpeak of peace, though it be in its remote principles, at never ſo great a diſtance from it; How ſafe I ſay, let our brethren judge. We have vvarping e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough already, the preſence of a fevv apprentiſes, hath made us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract Ordinances, hovv much more the preſence of the King looking ſmilingly for his ovvn advantages? vvhat if the King ſhould come in perſon to Treat, and He and the Parliament ſhould not agree, they ſtanding to their juſt and reaſonable demands in the Propoſitions, and the King vvithdravv his conſent? vvhat vvill fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovv in regard of hazard, and danger, he being brought ſo nigh us, before he hath given any ſecurity to us of our Liberties? we know Kings are ſtrange creaturs can carry that in their countenance which they never had in their hearts, and the influences, &amp; painted rayes of Majeſty on Subjects may work ſtrange things, which may be ſtrange indeed unto us. His Majeſtie hath had a great ſhare in the ruine of the Kingdome, he muſt be content to ſhare in the miſery, and abate ſomething of his honour to make up our loſſes; we ſhould joy in his Perſon if we had his heart, without which the other will doe us li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle good; the Kings honour lies in granting the juſt deſires of his Subjects in <hi>Parliament,</hi> and if he looks to his honour abſtractively, we muſt to our ſafety. We have little cauſe to put our necks under his Majeſties feet, and lye at his mercy.</p>
            <p>Beſides, neither can His Majeſty come alone without his traine; I mean thoſe Incendiaries which have been actors of this Deſigne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Kingdom; thoſe he calls friends, which the Parliament calls Delinquents: And I wiſh as his Perſon hath been ingaged with them in a bloody War, ſo his honour be not left with them. Its doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, He hath wrapt up his intereſts too much with theirs, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not honourably come himſelfe without good quarter for them: However, he will have an eye to them as his Favorites, and how ſafe we can thinke our ſelves, when ſuch ſhall be about His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, let our Brethren of <hi>Scotland</hi> judge.</p>
            <p>That Peace can only be Happy, which is ſuited to the firſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and Anſwers the ends of this War, which was to preſerve and ſettle Religion in power and purity, by countenancing the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:161405:9"/> profeſſors of it, and diſcountenancing the oppoſers; by this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the Biſhops themſelves might be likely to be accommodated, and thoſe outcaſts brought in State: And the ſecond ſtated end, was to bring Delinquents to juſtice, an Act of Oblivion will not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the juſt expectations and ingagements of the Kingdome, and we ſhall ſtill by it keepe the fuell of the ſame fire, or worſe within us, they will not ſo forget us, though we doe them, but when they grow up with us, will take their advantages to be quit with us; if we do not juſtice on them, God will on us: Can wee expect by ſuch a Treaty, that the King will ever ſuffer them to be plucked from his boſome, whoſe new Titles and Punctilioes of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, he will not ſuffer to be taken from their perſons? It is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain we cannot be ſafe, as long as they get heart, this generation will retain the ſeeds of this diſcontent; Impunity will but incourage them to act more when they have oportunity, yet ſtill as much fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour as can be ſhewn with the ſafety of the Kingdome muſt; ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice muſt be diſtributive, and proportionable to the perſons, and faults.</p>
            <p>In a word, ſuch a peace we muſt have, as may not let the guilt of blood be upon us. It can never enter into any ſerious heart, that the iſſue of all this blood, and the naturall product of all this ſtirres, ſhould be a ſlight and overly accommodation: Doubtleſſe God hath had his end, as well as men theirs, and that hath been working out, and we ought to expect it with faith, and patience, &amp; not run our ſelves on uncertain rocks, and skin over our ſores, when we may heale them; but no more of the Perſonall Treaty, (the golden bait our Brethren have laid before us, we ſhall have enough of it to our griefe, if ever providence ſhould permit ſuch an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,) only let me adde this; I know not why, if the Parliament have made war without the King, nay againſt his conſent, they may not make peace without him, eſpecially ſeeing he refuſeth to grant that which they judge eſſentiall to our happineſſe; we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with this, That the ſending honeſt and wary Propoſitions for his Majeſty to grant, is the beſt and ſafeſt way to procure a ſetled peace; if he be obſtinate, it muſt be done without him, there is no Medium, the Kingdome cannot alwayes languiſh. But our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren will not only have a perſonall Treaty the beſt way to peace, but adde the disbanding of the Army, without which the grant
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:161405:10"/> of the former will not ſerve: This Propoſition they urge from the tenderneſſe of the ſenſe they have of the taxes, and burthens of this Kingdome, in regard of free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quarter, and Contributions; (for this thanks muſt ſtill be returned,) but I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our Brethren loſt their ſenſe of <hi>Englands</hi> burthens in the North, where beſides free-quarter, and plunderings, they laid ſuch a ſeſſe, that the fiſh in the ſea could not ſcape their tax: However, I am glad they are come to their ſenſes at laſt, we hope, they will be ſenſible to abate ſome things of their hundred thouſands we owe them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> out of brotherly aſſiſtance: the reflections on thoſe gallant men (of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my) I will not mention; its a ſad thing that faithfulneſſe ſhould be the ground of ſuſpition, and the object of envy. Whereas they ſay, that they expected on the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding of their Army in <hi>Scotland,</hi> we ſhould disband ours. Its a wonder, with what face of reaſon they could urge that, ſeeing that we have work to do, which they have not; they know the ends of keeping up their Army, and we know ours, the Parliament are not bound to give an account to the Commiſſioners why they keep up their Army, and though they are pleaſed to ſay there is no uſe for them now, they muſt know, they go about to make uſe for them. <hi>England</hi> was the firſt ſeat of War, and moſt diſtempered, and that will not ſettle us, which will <hi>Scotlan;</hi> we have conquered our enemies perſons, we had need have an Army to keep down their ſpirits: What is the matter our brethren have ſuch an eye at this Army? Is it becauſe they have been too faithfull? Have done too much ſervice which they would fain have the honour of? It may be they have conquered thoſe, which our Brethren were in hopes to conquer, and get the ſpoil of. It may be the reaſons are, becauſe the <hi>London</hi> Apprentices and Reformadoes, may more handſomly come, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet the Houſes of Parliament and make them V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e in the old Militia, and cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> down Independents, and ſuch like tricks; but I hope they are more ſerious, and therefore I recall my words; it is, that the Parliament may be disbanded more handſomly, and be made the next burthen to the Kingdom, and the <hi>Scots</hi> may have a new Covenant with the King, to be his Loyall Subjects: If the Army become a burthen, the Kingdome may thank them, and their Party, who could not carry it ſo fairely and wiſely, as to disband them Honourably at firſt. The violence and raſhneſſe of thoſe men, gave them ground enough of diſtaſte then, and ſtill ground of jealouſie; let peace be ſetled, they will ſoon disband: Its reaſon, that if they have fought for peace, they ſhould not disband untill they ſee tearms agreed on, and things put in a hopefull way of ſecurity for the Kingdom and themſelves: they have made many propoſals for the good of the Kingdome, and if they have failed in cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, we may well overlook that; now they are freed of their popular Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, we may well be free from Jealouſies of them: If in any thing they have miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carried, its becauſe ſome of them have been at court as well as the <hi>Scots</hi> Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, but I have ſaid too much on theſe things, more then will pleaſe I am ſure; I wiſh they would give leſſe occaſion to the Parliament and <hi>Engliſh</hi> men, to make Anti-Declarations. There only remaines to add, what we are to indeavour parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly for the ſtabliſhing of a well grounded Peace: I know wiſer men have it in hand, I wiſh they may in their hearts alſo. I only offer ſomething to inform the people what they muſt ſtick to, if they will finde the way to peace.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing muſt be the ſettlement of Religion in the power and purity of it, and in this our Brethrens order of giving it the preeminence, is to be commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but I hope by Religion, they do not only mean the Presbyterian Government;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:161405:10"/> Miniſters muſt be ſent out to preach the Goſpel, and inform poor ſouls in the things of Chriſt, this will be a good foundation of our happineſſe.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing mainly to be eyed is the preſervation of the Union of the two Kingdoms, by all the lawfull wayes we can, according to the true intent and proper ſenſe of the Covenant; the ſtrengthening of ſuch a mutuall correſpondence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us will increaſe our happineſſe; yet care muſt be taken that we interfere not in our proper priviledges; even reckoning, and fair ſtating of our peculiar concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments will keep us long friends.</p>
            <p>Next in order to this, what concerns our own particulars, and are moſt funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall to our future happineſſe, muſt be propoſed, and not moved from. Theſe things are,</p>
            <p>Firſt. The Priviledges and Authority of Parliaments; our liberty and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is bound up in them, if they be diſcountenanced, diſcontinued, diſeſteemed, ſo ſhall wee be too; we muſt therefore be very wary of entertaining hard thoughts of them, or reflecting on their proceedings, that is the great advantage our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies now look at: this Parliament muſt be continued, untill it hath done the work of this ſeaſon.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The happineſſe of our Peace will lye in the eſtabliſhing of good Laws, repealing bad, or inconvenient ones, and in a ſpeedy and direct way for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable execution of them; if our Lawes be never ſo good, they will not be ſo to us; if they be not in good hands to execute them; the influences of them will be cold and deſtructive, if they have bad Interpreters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we know formerly, how good Laws have been made uſe of againſt good men.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The power of the <hi>Militia</hi> muſt be put in thoſe whom the <hi>Parliament</hi> can truſt, and though we are hardly able to find ſuch as could be wiſhed, yet we muſt take ſuch as we can, and are moſt cleer of ſcandall, and have given beſt teſtimony of their faithfulnes to the Kingdome. The next thing, which might have been put in the firſt rank, in regard of the concernment of it, is an indeavour to unite among our ſelves, untill this be done we ſhall be to ſeek of ſuch a deſired peace; Something muſt be given in by each party as a ſacrifice to this Deſign; nothing undoes us but this; that we ſtrive to ſtrengthen parties, and doe not our parts to compoſe our diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences. And unto this muſt be added a conſtant cying of our publike enemy; ſome diſtinction muſt be put on them, whereby they may be known, and obſerved in their actings; while this Generation laſts, their grudge will laſt againſt our peace above all things; (that ſo we may be out of fear againſt next <hi>Parliament</hi>) ſomething muſt be done to take away their Votes (vvho have been in Armes, and are adjudged Delinquents) in election of Burgeſſes; for elſe we are like to be as we were, yea more ſad; for they are ſo numerous, and deſperate, that they will over-vote all the <hi>Parliaments</hi> party, and at length think of revenge by ſuch an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; they will ſoone have a <hi>Parliament</hi> of the old ſtrain, to make us more miſerable; and what act of this <hi>Parliament</hi> can bind the next? I would this haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard were more ſeriouſly in the hearts of men, I knovv nothing of more ominous conſequence, then the allowing ſuch a priviledge to Delinquents, neither is it rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that thoſe who have fought againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> ſhould have their Vote in the choſing of them again: Beſides, God requires ſomething as well as reaſon, to be done in way of diſtinction to them who have acted in ſuch a deſperate Deſigne;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:161405:11"/> the <hi>Parliament</hi> will find few or no friends, if their enemies be brought up in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall priviledge with them. But ſome will ſay, what ſhall be done with the King all this while the <hi>Parliament</hi> is about Propoſitions with him, and if he will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the termes of our Peace, we muſt preſerve him, and our ſelves as we can. The <hi>Parliament</hi> vvill take care of his Perſon with honour, and ſafety, and wait on God to change his heart, in the mean time to proceed without him, and ſee to the ſetling of the Kingdome; great care muſt be taken for the ſatisfying the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> ingagements to the Kingdome, paying their debts, performing their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, that publike faith may be had in reverence; eſpecially ſomething muſt be done for <hi>meum &amp; tuum,</hi> that the poore people may ſee Juſtice running like ſtreams by their own doors; this would ingage people much, and indear them to the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament;</hi> that the vulgar: may be able to ſay this I have got by this <hi>Parliament</hi> that I could not have before; this mechanick kind of Juſtice, as its moſt honeſt, ſo its moſt profitable; let people ſee ſome things viſible that they may find in their plowing and ſowing, in their bargains and eſtates, and they would never be againſt the <hi>Parliament</hi> more. Let thoſe eſpecially which have been moſt forward, and active, and faithfull, have moſt of the influences of the peace upon them, and then wee ſhall act like wiſe men, and honeſt men. Many things might be added which are not ſo conſiderable as theſe. I ſhall not want cenſures for theſe; I can onely wiſh men honeſter, or wiſer. <hi>Si populus vult decipi decipiatur;</hi> If we will be fools we ſhall ſoon be ſlaves. If we wince, and ſeek to caſt off the eaſie burrhen, that will be but for a time, till things ſettle, we may ſinke for ever under the intollerable miſchief of an unſettlement, and perhaps, Tyranny and perpetuall flavery attend the iſſue. If we will not ſee our happineſſe, we ſhall quickly our miſery. I cannot better conclude all, than with this deſire to all thoſe which have any Engliſh bloud yet left in their veins, (or any ſenſe of true liberty) that as they have valiantly fought for peace, ſo they would conſiderately weigh and ſtand to the terms of Peace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Scot,</hi> or whoever attempt to encroach upon, or enſlave this Nation. You are yet in the greateſt hazzard: Have not your own hands been your deſtruction? Doe not loſe all by playing one card. Your enemies are waiting to ſee your folly, and their own advantage; and many of your pretended friends ſecretly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine you; leave nothing out you can foreſee, and truſt not men further then you ſee; our condition is ſad, and the worſe, becauſe we are ſo; but remember you are Engliſh men, when you think of <hi>Scotland,</hi> wait on the Lord, ſeek his face, and he will yet appear.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
